Hi, this is Matt Baker. Last year, I did
a series of videos on who was Jesus
really. In these videos, I looked at
some rather far out hypotheses. Not
because I thought any of them were
likely to be true, but because I thought
it would be a fun way to introduce some
of the historical context relating to
Jesus. Well, in today's video, I'm going
to switch gears and finally address the
question in a more serious manner
because there is in fact a general
consensus among scholars about who the
historical Jesus actually was. Of
course, Christian scholars say that he
was God incarnate. But what I'm talking
about here is what secular scholars have
concluded. And what most secular
scholars have concluded is that Jesus
was an apocalyptic prophet who was
killed for stirring up trouble in
Jerusalem during one of the annual
Passover festivals. These days, the
leading scholar on the historical Jesus
is, in my opinion, Bart Erman. So take
note that much of what I'll be covering
today is based on his books. in
particular, Jesus, the apocalyptic
prophet of the new millennium, and how
Jesus became God, the exaltation of a
Jewish preacher from Galilee. But before
we jump into it, I want to give you an
update on another project I've been
working on, and that is improving my
French, thanks to today's sponsor,
Babel. Babel is one of the top language
learning apps in the world, and I've
been using it for around 3 months now as
a way to challenge myself to improve my
pronunciation of foreign words. Of the
many different languages it offers, I
chose to start with French because,
well, I'm Canadian and therefore I felt
that I should at least be able to
pronounce French words correctly. Let me
show you a lesson I did recently and you
tell me how I did.
Bonjour.
We say
now, if you are also interested in
trying Babel, but are not quite sure if
it's going to work out well for you, the
good news is that they have a 20-day
money back guarantee. And right now is a
great time to try it out because they're
currently offering 55% off. So click on
my link right now to give Babel a try.
Now back to the historical Jesus. So the
first thing I have to explain is what an
apocalyptic prophet is. To do that,
let's go back around 750 years before
Jesus and look at the role that prophets
originally played in ancient Israel and
Judah. So this is my timeline of
biblical composition chart. As you can
see, the oldest books in the entire
Hebrew Bible are Amos, Hosea, Micah, and
Isaiah. Take note that both Micah and
Isaiah were added to later. So when it
comes to those two, I'm referring to the
first portions of the books only. What
all four of these early prophets have in
common is that they were writing during
the time when the northern kingdom of
Israel was about to fall to the Assyrian
Empire. So their goal was to prevent
this from happening by trying to
convince the Israelites to change their
ways. But here's the important thing.
Their message was to the nation as a
whole, not to each person individually.
And their focus was on one particular
sin, not bad behavior in general. And
that one particular sin was idolatry. So
the message was stop worshiping other
gods and turn back to the one true god,
the one known by the four letters yhwh.
If you do that, God will help you defeat
the Assyrians. Well, we know how the
story goes. The Israelites did not
defeat the Assyrians, although the
southern kingdom of Judah did. Thus, the
worship of YHW flourished there, at
least for a while. But then a new enemy
entered the scene, the Babylonians. So,
more prophets were sent again with a
similar message to the entire nation.
Stop worshiping other gods. If you turn
back to the one true God, you will
survive. But again, this didn't happen.
Judah fell to the Babylonians. Now later
the Persians did let the Judahites
return to Jerusalem and rebuild their
temple. But even though the Judahites,
now called Jews, were careful to worship
the one true God only, they remained
under foreign rule. Thus, the message of
the prophets started to change. To
demonstrate this, let me show you two
very different verses from the Hebrew
Bible. The first one is from Exodus 20,
which is part of a very old law code
that was likely written way back here
around 750 B.CE. It says, "You shall not
bow down to other gods or worship them.
For I, the Lord your God, am a jealous
God, punishing the children for the sin
of the parents to the third and fourth
generation." Contrast this with what was
written about 300 years later in the
book of Ezekiel around 450 B.CE. The one
who sins is the one who will die. The
child will not share the guilt of the
parent, nor will the parent share the
guilt of the child. The righteousness of
the righteous will be credited to them,
and the wickedness of the wicked will be
charged against them. So, first of all,
there's a shift from national sins to
individual sins. But that's not the only
difference. In Ezekiel as well as in
Zechariah and Joel, we find some of the
earliest apocalyptic visions. The word
apocalyptic comes from the Greek
apocalypsis, which means an unveiling of
something hidden. So instead of prophets
talking about real physical armies that
are about to attack, they instead start
talking about invisible entities
representing good and evil that are
fighting each other in an unseen spirit
realm. You see, the idea is that
although the good guys always seem to
lose down here on Earth, that's just
because the unseen battle that is going
on upstairs hasn't yet finished. But
when it does, everything will be okay
because then the triumphant forces of
good will come down to earth and make
things right here as well. Even the
righteous dead will be resurrected. By
the time we get to Daniel, which was the
very last book in the Hebrew Bible to be
written, these ideas had been fleshed
out even more. In Daniel 7, we learned
that one like a son of man would
eventually appear in the clouds and that
this figure with God's permission would
then come down to earth and rule all
nations. Now in the Hebrew Bible, the
term son of man or sons of man occurs
about 100 times and in each case it
always refers to a human being or humans
in general. So, in other words, the
phrase son of man can basically be
swapped out for the word human. But take
note, the author of Daniel doesn't say
that a human would appear in the clouds.
He says that one like a human would. So,
the idea is that some sort of spiritual
being that looks like a human, perhaps
an angel, would eventually appear. In
subsequent apocalyptic literature, this
spiritual being is simply referred to as
the son of man. And his future rule on
earth is simply referred to as the
kingdom of God. But remember, the son of
man was not God, nor was he a human. He
was something in between. Again, the
closest concept we have for such a being
is that of an angel. And we do know that
the ancient Jews did believe in angels.
So the message that an apocalyptic
prophet brings is don't worry, the evil
world that you're experiencing right now
is going to end very soon. So shape up
and be good so that when the son of man
comes, you can be part of the new
kingdom of God. Which brings us to Jesus
because a lot of what Jesus said was
along these same lines especially when
we look at Matthew, Mark, and Luke which
are our earliest sources as opposed to
John which was written later. For
example, Jesus often references this son
of man character like in Mark where he
says, "Whoever is ashamed of me and my
words of that person will the son of man
also be ashamed when he comes." Now, if
you're a Christian or a former
Christian, you're probably used to
assuming that whenever Jesus refers to
the Son of Man, he's referring to
himself. But if you take his words at
face value and put yourself in the place
of the people who first heard those
words, it actually makes more sense to
assume that he is talking about someone
else, a figure that everyone was
familiar with who had not yet come.
Jesus also talked a lot about the
kingdom of God. In fact, his very first
words in Mark are, "The time has come.
The kingdom of God is almost here." A
few chapters later, he's way more
specific. He says, "I tell you the
truth, there are some standing here
today who will not taste death until
they see the kingdom of God come in
power." Now, Christians are taught to
understand this as referring to Jesus's
resurrection and the giving of the Holy
Spirit. But to the people who were
listening at the time, they would
definitely have interpreted it in the
Jewish apocalyptic sense, they would
have understood it to mean that the
Romans were about to be crushed and that
the kingdom of God was about to be
established on earth within their own
lifetimes. Hence, the urgency to repent
and make changes to their life right
then and there. On top of this, all of
Jesus's actions were basically him
modeling what the sooncoming kingdom of
God was going to look like. So soon
there would be no more disease, hence
Jesus healed the sick. Soon there would
be no more war, hence Jesus encouraged
nonviolence. And soon there would be no
more poverty, hence Jesus told people to
give away their possessions in order to
help the poor. But here's the really
important one. Soon the current temple
would be replaced with a new one. Hence,
Jesus went to the temple and flipped
over a bunch of tables, creating a
scene. It was this final symbolic
gesture that likely got him in trouble.
From the Christian perspective, the
story of Jesus and the money changers at
the temple is not all that important.
It's just one of the many strange things
that Jesus did during his time on Earth.
But when it comes to the historical
Jesus, it very well might be the most
important part of the story. You see,
it's included in all four gospels. Yet,
like I say, it's not really all that
central to the Christian message. In
fact, it kind of goes against how Jesus
is usually portrayed, which is very
gentle and nonviolent. Therefore, it is
very likely that this is one of the
events recorded in the Gospels that did
in fact actually happen. Now, it may
seem odd that the Romans would have
killed a guy just for flipping over some
tables. But you see, there was an
additional aspect to Jesus's teachings
that only he and his inner circle knew
about. In fact, the gospel writers make
it super clear that he wanted to keep
this part secret. And the secret was
that when the kingdom of God was
established, Jesus was going to be in
charge with his 12 disciples ruling
directly under him. Now the word used in
the gospels for Jesus being in charge is
Messiah. And here once again it's
important to put aside later notions of
what the word Messiah means and think
about what it meant in its original
context because in its original context
it simply meant anointed one or king or
ruler. So let me set the scene for you.
It's Passover week and the situation is
really tense because Jerusalem is super
crowded, especially with out oftowners
who the Romans saw as potential
troublemakers. Remember also that
Passover was literally a holiday
designed to remind the Jews of a time
when they escaped from foreign rule. So,
the Romans would definitely have been on
guard for any potential threats. Then
during this intense week, the normally
passive Jesus makes a big scene at the
temple and all of the sudden he and his
disciples are under close scrutiny. One
of the 12, Judas, gets scared and
basically rats Jesus out, telling the
authorities what Jesus had said in
secret about being a future ruler. Then
Jesus gets pulled in before Pilate
doesn't deny it. So just to be on the
safe side, Pilate has him crucified. And
that's basically who Jesus was. Just one
of many apocalyptic prophets in first
century Judea who were out there telling
people that the world as they knew it
was about to end and who got himself in
deep trouble for doing so. So how did he
go from that to being thought of as God
incarnate? Well, first of all, imagine
it from the perspective of his
followers. They like many others over
the centuries really believed that the
world was about to end and that they had
been chosen by God for a very special
purpose. Thus, instead of simply
abandoning all their deeply held beliefs
after Jesus died, they simply tweaked
them a bit. We know that it's a very
common psychological phenomenon for
people to have visions of dead loved
ones, especially in cases when the death
was very unexpected and/or traumatic. We
also know that it's a very common
psychological phenomenon for people in
tight-knit religious groups to all claim
to have had the same experience. So,
think about it from the perspective of
someone who believed in apocalyptic
Judaism. They think that the
resurrection of the dead is coming soon.
And now they have a dead person, their
leader, [clears throat]
talking to them. So, maybe he's just the
first of many to be raised from the
dead. Maybe he's the son of man who's
going to return soon to usher in the
kingdom of God. That would make sense to
them because after all, he said he was
going to be the anointed one. Thus, the
earliest form of Christianity is born.
One in which Jesus was a human who then
after death was exalted by God to a
special position in preparation for the
sooncoming apocalypse. Bart Earman calls
this early form of the religion
exaltation Christianity. And
interestingly within the writings of
Paul, we have the traces of some very
early creeds which were most likely
originally oral creeds that quite
clearly represent this view. For
example, at the very beginning of the
epistle to the Romans, there's a section
that stands out as being highly
structured and which uses words that
Paul does not use anywhere else. It goes
like this. Who was descended from the
seed of David according to the flesh who
was appointed son of God in power
according to the spirit of holiness.
Take note that there's no mention of an
empty tomb here. And no mention of Jesus
ever having existed prior to his earthly
life. Just him being appointed or
exalted after his death. And just
because it uses the phrase son of God,
that doesn't mean that whoever wrote
this thought of Jesus as being equal to
God. In fact, in those days, the term
son or sons of God was often used to
refer to angels. In fact, there is
another verse in the Pauline epistles
that makes it clear that Paul thought of
Jesus as an angel, not as God. In
Galatians 4:14,
he writes, "Though my condition was a
trial to you, you did not scorn or
despise me, but received me as an angel
of God, as Christ Jesus." Now, the
assumption made by Christians is that he
meant you treated me like an angel. No,
even better. You treated me like Jesus.
But the Greek here is actually quite
clear. It means you treated me like an
angel. an angel such as Jesus. Okay, so
the earliest form of Christianity had
Jesus simply being exalted to an
angel-like position after death so that
he could now take on the role of the Son
of Man, who would appear in the clouds
and usher in the kingdom of God. All of
which the earliest Christians still
expected would occur within their own
lifetimes. One piece of evidence for
this is the fact that Paul says in 1
Thessalonians, "For the Lord himself
will come down from heaven, and the dead
in Christ will rise first. After that,
we who are still alive and are left will
be caught up together with them in the
clouds to meet the Lord in the air." So,
the expectation was that some would die,
but also that some would still be living
when Jesus came back. Now, pretty
quickly, debates arose over the exact
details of who Jesus was. Some started
to think that maybe he had already been
an angel while he was here on earth.
Others thought that maybe he had been an
angel before he was born on earth. This
last idea quickly evolved into what man
calls incarnation Christianity. The idea
being that Jesus was an already existing
spiritual being who was then incarnated
into a human body. Paul in particular
liked this idea and combined it with the
idea that Jesus's death paid for our
sins. But then the author of John who
wrote the very last gospel 70 plus years
after the crucifixion took things even
further. He equated Jesus with God
himself. You see, by this point,
Jerusalem and its temple had been
completely destroyed, and Jesus had
quite clearly not come back. Therefore,
Christianity started to shift away from
its original apocalyptic message and
more towards its salvation message,
which now had Jesus as the replacement
for the now destroyed temple. But don't
assume that everybody was happy with
this particular version of Christianity
this early on because it would take the
new religion over 200 more years for the
majority of its leaders to finally agree
on it and several more hundred years
before all the other variations of
Christianity were stamped out. So there
you have it. That is who Jesus was
according to most secular scholars. He
was an apocalyptic prophet who taught
that the world was going to end soon.
But he got himself killed by stating
that he was going to be the ruler in the
future kingdom of God. Only later in the
decades after his death was Jesus
reinterpreted to fit the needs of those
he left behind. So that brings us to the
end of this particular series. In
another month or so, I'll do what I've
done with my other religion series, and
that is to combine all of the episodes
into one single video for easier sharing
and accessing in the future. Thanks for
watching.